<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../dtd/docbook/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ********************************************************************
     $Id$
     ******************************************************************** -->

<chapter id="prop-startup-delay">
    <title>wrapper.startup.delay Property</title>
    <section>
        <title>Configuration Property Overview</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html">Configuration Property Overview</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="props-advanced.html">Advanced Properties</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html#name">Property List by Name</ulink>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>wrapper.startup.delay</title>
        <para>
            Controls the number of seconds to pause between the Wrapper being launched
            and the first JVM being launched.  Defaults to 0 seconds.
        </para>
        <para>
            Most applications will want to maintain a startup delay of 0, but
            there are some cases where system resources may not be immediately
            available after a system restart for example.  In general, it is
            recommended to make the Java application being run, robust enough
            to handle such problems.   However where that is not possible, this
            property may be useful.
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <simpara><emphasis>Example:</emphasis></simpara>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[wrapper.startup.delay=30]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <para>
            It may be necessary to have a startup delay when running as a service
            under windows.  However having such a delay at all times would be
            inconvenient when the application is being run from a console.  The
            Wrapper provides two variants of this property which make it
            possible to specify different startup delays depending on whether
            the Wrapper is being run as a service or a console application.
        </para>
        <para>
            The service delay is specified using the
            <literal moreinfo="none">wrapper.startup.delay.service</literal>
            property, and the console mode delay using the
            <literal moreinfo="none">wrapper.startup.delay.console</literal>
            property.   If either property is not specified, it defaults to
            the value of <literal moreinfo="none">wrapper.startup.delay</literal>.
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <simpara><emphasis>Example:</emphasis></simpara>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[wrapper.startup.delay.console=0
wrapper.startup.delay.service=30]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <para>
            On UNIX platforms, the Wrapper is running as a service if its
            <ulink url="prop-daemonize.html">wrapper.daemonize</ulink> property
            is set.  The sh script, provided with the Wrapper, will set the
            wrapper.daemonize property if the <literal moreinfo="none">start</literal>
            command is used when.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
