<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../dtd/docbook/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ********************************************************************
     $Id$
     ******************************************************************** -->

<chapter id="prop-ntservice-process-priority">
    <title>wrapper.ntservice.process_priority Property</title>
    <section>
        <title>Configuration Property Overview</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html">Configuration Property Overview</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="props-nt.html">Windows NT/2000/XP Configuration Properties</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html#name">Property List by Name</ulink>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>wrapper.ntservice.process_priority</title>
        <para>
            Specifies the priority at which the Wrapper and its JVM will be run
            at when run as an NT service or as a console application.  Possible
            values are
            <literal moreinfo="none">LOW</literal>,
            <literal moreinfo="none">BELOW_NORMAL</literal>,
            <literal moreinfo="none">NORMAL</literal>,
            <literal moreinfo="none">ABOVE_NORMAL</literal>,
            <literal moreinfo="none">HIGH</literal>, and
            <literal moreinfo="none">REALTIME</literal>.  Defaults to
            <literal moreinfo="none">NORMAL</literal>.
            <literal moreinfo="none">BELOW_NORMAL</literal> and
            <literal moreinfo="none">ABOVE_NORMAL</literal> are not supported on
            Windows NT, 95 or 98.
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <simpara><emphasis>Example:</emphasis></simpara>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[wrapper.ntservice.process_priority=NORMAL]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <warning>
            <para>
                Changing this property to HIGH or REALTIME makes the Wrapper and its JVM consume
                all available CPU first.  It will only yield CPU to other processes when it does
                not need the cycles itself.  This will cause a number of problems including an
                unresponsive UI.
            </para>
            <para>
                We have seen problems with time-outs, between the Wrapper and its JVM, when the
                JVM is outputting large quantities of console output and consuming 100%, for
                long periods of time.  If you change this default value and are experiencing
                such time-outs, please return the property to the default NORMAL priority
                before contacting support.
            </para>
        </warning>
        <note>
            <para>
                <ulink url="prop-restart-reload-configuration.html">Reloading</ulink>
                the Wrapper configuration will have no effect on the priority of the Wrapper
                process.  But the priority of the restarted JVM process will take on the
                updated value.
            </para>
        </note>
        <note>
            <simpara>
                From the Windows API, each priority level is described as
                follows:
            </simpara>
            <glosslist>
                <glossentry>
                    <glossterm>NORMAL</glossterm>
                    <glossdef>
                        <para>
                            Specify this class for a process with no
                            special scheduling needs.
                        </para>
                    </glossdef>
                </glossentry>
                <glossentry>
                    <glossterm>LOW</glossterm>
                    <glossdef>
                        <para>
                            Specify this class for a process whose threads
                            run only when the system is idle. The threads
                            of the process are preempted by the threads of
                            any process running in a higher priority class.
                            An example is a screen saver. The idle-priority
                            class is inherited by child processes.
                        </para>
                    </glossdef>
                </glossentry>
                <glossentry>
                    <glossterm>HIGH</glossterm>
                    <glossdef>
                        <para>
                            Specify this class for a process that performs
                            time-critical tasks that must be executed
                            immediately. The threads of the process preempt
                            the threads of normal or idle priority class
                            processes. An example is the Task List, which
                            must respond quickly when called by the user,
                            regardless of the load on the operating system.
                            Use extreme care when using the high-priority
                            class, because a high-priority class
                            application can use nearly all available CPU
                            time.
                        </para>
                    </glossdef>
                </glossentry>
                <glossentry>
                    <glossterm>REALTIME</glossterm>
                    <glossdef>
                        <para>
                            Specify this class for a process that has the
                            highest possible priority. The threads of the
                            process preempt the threads of all other
                            processes, including operating system processes
                            performing important tasks. For example, a
                            real-time process that executes for more than
                            a very brief interval can cause disk caches not
                            to flush or cause the mouse to be unresponsive.
                        </para>
                    </glossdef>
                </glossentry>
            </glosslist>
        </note>
    </section>
</chapter>
