<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../dtd/docbook/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ********************************************************************
     $Id$
     ******************************************************************** -->

<chapter id="prop-startup-timeout">
    <title>wrapper.startup.timeout Property</title>
    <section>
        <title>Configuration Property Overview</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html">Configuration Property Overview</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="props-advanced.html">Advanced Properties</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html#name">Property List by Name</ulink>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>wrapper.startup.timeout</title>
        <para>
            Number of seconds to allow between the time that the Wrapper
            launches the JVM process and the time that the JVM side of the
            Wrapper responds that the application has started.  0 means never
            time out.  Defaults to 30 seconds.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you are experiencing timeout problems as your application is
            starting up.  The most common cause is a misconfiguration.  Please
            verify that the <literal moreinfo="none">WrapperManager</literal>
            is indeed being started.  You should see the following output in
            the console when you launch the Wrapper.
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[wrapper  | --> Wrapper Started as Console
wrapper  | Launching a JVM...
jvm 1    | Wrapper (Version 3.x.x)]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <para>
            If you do not see the Wrapper version displayed, then the
            <literal moreinfo="none">WrapperManager</literal> is not being
            launched.  Please make sure that you have read over the
            <ulink url="integrate.html">Integration</ulink>
            section.  If the configuration looks correct, then try enabling
            DEBUG level log output to try and narrow in on the problem.
        </para>
        <para>
            If the Wrapper version is being displayed, but the Wrapper is still
            timing out on startup, then it is most likely being caused by one
            of two things.  The first is that the start method call is not
            returning.  This should not be an issue if you are using the
            <literal moreinfo="none">SimpleWrapperApp</literal> or
            <literal moreinfo="none">SimpleStartStopApp</literal> classes to
            launch your application.   If you are implementing the
            <literal moreinfo="none">WrapperListener</literal> however, please
            verify that the <literal moreinfo="none">start</literal> method is
            indeed returning upon completion.  You should be able to see this
            with <literal moreinfo="none">DEBUG</literal> output enabled.
        </para>
        <para>
            The other possibility is that the startup method is simply taking
            a while to complete.  In this case, it may be necessary to extend
            the default startup timeout.  Try setting to to 300 (5 minutes)
            and see if that makes the problem go away.
        </para>
        <para>
            It is best to choose a value which is long enough to let the
            application start reliably, but short enough that the Wrapper will
            react as quickly as possible in the event of an actual JVM hang.
        </para>
        <para>
            If the start procedure sometimes takes a long time.  One
            alternative to setting a long timeout is to periodically call the 
            <literal moreinfo="none">WrapperManager.signalStarting(n)</literal>
            method.  This method gives the application the ability to request
            more time to startup, while at the same time assuring the Wrapper
            that the JVM is alive and well.
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <simpara><emphasis>Example:</emphasis></simpara>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[wrapper.startup.timeout=30]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <warning>
            <simpara>
                While the ability is there.  Be aware that
                setting this property to 0 or some large value will mean
                that the Wrapper's ability to detect a JVM hang during the
                startup phase will be disabled.
            </simpara>
        </warning>
    </section>
</chapter>
