<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../dtd/docbook/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ********************************************************************
     $Id$
     ******************************************************************** -->

<chapter id="prop-ntservice-account">
    <title>wrapper.ntservice.account Property</title>
    <section>
        <title>Configuration Property Overview</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html">Configuration Property Overview</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="props-nt.html">Windows NT/2000/XP Configuration Properties</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html#name">Property List by Name</ulink>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>wrapper.ntservice.account</title>
        <para>
            The account to use when running the service.  Use an account name in
            the form: <literal moreinfo="none">{DomainName}\{UserName}</literal>.
            If the account belongs to the built-in domain, then you may specify
            the name if the form: <literal moreinfo="none">.\{UserName}</literal>.
            The default, blank value, will use the LocalSystem account.
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <simpara><emphasis>Example:</emphasis></simpara>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[wrapper.ntservice.account=.\leif]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <para>
            When attempting to install the service, you will encounter the
            following message if the account name is invalid, does not exist, or
            the password for the account is incorrect.  A common mistake is
            setting the account name to <literal moreinfo="none">leif</literal>
            rather than <literal moreinfo="none">.\leif</literal>.
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[CreateService failed - The account name is invalid or does not exist,
or the password is invalid for the account name specified. (0x421)]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <para>
            Only accounts which have their "Logon as Service" right set can be
            used to run a service.  Failure to set this right will result in the
            following error message when you attempt to actually start the
            service:
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[System error 1069 has occurred.

The service did not start due to a logon failure.]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <para>
            To set the "Logon as Service" right;  Go to the Administrative Tools
            folder in your control panel.  Open the Local Security Policy applet.
            Expand Local Policy and then click on User Rights Assignment.  On
            the right side there is a logon as service policy.  Open that and
            then add the user that you wish to allow to run the service.
        </para>
        <para>
            Note that the Local Security Policy applet does not appear to be
            available on Home versions of Windows 2000 and XP.  It is thus not
            possible to run a service as a specific account under those versions
            of Windows.
        </para>
        <note>
            <para>
                The <ulink url="prop-ntservice-interactive.html">wrapper.ntservice.interactive</ulink>
                property must be set to FALSE if the service is configured to run using a specific
                account.
            </para>
        </note>
        <note>
            <para>
                Changes to this property will not take effect until the
                service is reinstalled.
            </para>
        </note>
    </section>
</chapter>
