<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../dtd/docbook/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ********************************************************************
     $Id$
     ******************************************************************** -->

<chapter id="prop-pidfile">
    <title>wrapper.pidfile Property</title>
    <section>
        <title>Configuration Property Overview</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html">Configuration Property Overview</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="props-advanced.html">Advanced Properties</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html#name">Property List by Name</ulink>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>wrapper.pidfile</title>
        <para>
            File to write the Wrapper process ID to.  If set, a file containing the
            pid of the Wrapper process will be written to the specified location
            when the process is launched.  The file will be deleted when the
            Wrapper process has terminated.  This property is not set by default.
            Common values are <literal moreinfo="none">./myapp.pid</literal> or
            <literal moreinfo="none">/var/run/myapp.pid</literal>.
        </para>
        <note>
            <para>
                If a second instance of the Wrapper is started, the pid file of the
                first instance will be overwritten by the second instance.  This is
                done to avoid problems with stale pid files preventing the wrapper
                from starting.
            </para>
            <para>
                On Unix/Linux platforms, the <literal moreinfo="none">sh</literal>
                script which ships with the Wrapper will prevent multiple copies of
                the Wrapper from running for the same application.  It is possible
                to run multiple copies of the Wrapper on the same machine if they
                are each being used to launch a different application.
            </para>
        </note>
        <para>
            In most cases, users will not need to set this property themselves.  The
            Unix <literal moreinfo="none">sh</literal> script which ship with the
            Wrapper sets this property from the command line and then makes use of
            the pid in future invocations of the script.  See the
            <literal moreinfo="none">sh.script.in</literal> file in the
            <literal moreinfo="none">src/bin</literal> directory for an example.
        </para>
        <para>
            The property is also available in the Windows version as some users have
            requested easy access to the pid for use by profiling tools.
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <simpara><emphasis>Example:</emphasis></simpara>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[wrapper.pidfile=./myapp.pid]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <note>
            <para>
                <ulink url="prop-restart-reload-configuration.html">Reloading</ulink>
                the Wrapper configuration will have no effect on the value of this property.
                Changes will not take effect until the Wrapper has been restarted.
            </para>
        </note>
    </section>
</chapter>
