<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../dtd/docbook/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ********************************************************************
     $Id$
     ******************************************************************** -->

<chapter id="api-overview">
 
    <title>Application debugging</title> 

    <section>
        <title>Debugging Your Java Application using the Wrapper</title>
        <para>
            The Wrapper offers some simple features which will aid you in tracking down
            any problems that you may be having with your application.
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Requesting a Thread Dump</title>
            <para>
                The Wrapper contains support for requesting that the JVM dump out its current
                state.  The exact contents of the information will vary depending on which JVM
                is being run.
            </para>
            <para>
                The Sun JVMs will display the stack traces of all running threads to the console.
            </para>
            <para>
                IBM JVMs provide even more useful information.  The stack traces of all threads
                as well as object monitor states are dumped to the console.  In addition a file
                is created in the current directory which in addition to the information shown
                in the console also contains useful information about the system including all
                of the environment variables.
            </para>
            <para>
                A Thread Dump can be requested on Windows systems by pressing CTRL-BREAK or on
                Linux systems by pressing CTRL-\.  Invoking a thread dump does not affect the
                JVM.  It will continue to run normally.
            </para>
            <para>
                The startup for Linux and Solaris provided with the Wrapper installation, launch
                the Wrapper in a background thread.  To request a thread dump using these scripts,
                simply rerun the script specifying the 'dump' parameter.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Enabling Debug Logging</title>
            <para>
                Many configuration problems can be quickly resolved by setting the log level
                of the console output to DEBUG.  The full command used to launch Java as well
                as version information on the JVM being run will then be displayed in the
                console.  See the
                <ulink url="props-logging.html">Logging Configuration Properties</ulink>
                section for more information.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section> 
</chapter>
