<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../dtd/docbook/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ********************************************************************
     $Id$
     ******************************************************************** -->

<chapter id="prop-ping-timeout">
    <title>wrapper.ping.timeout Property</title>
    <section>
        <title>Configuration Property Overview</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html">Configuration Property Overview</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="props-advanced.html">Advanced Properties</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html#name">Property List by Name</ulink>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>wrapper.ping.timeout</title>
        <para>
            Number of seconds to allow between the wrapper pinging the JVM and
            the response.  0 means never time out.  Defaults to 30 seconds.
        </para>
        <para>
            The ping timeout must be at least 5 seconds longer than the value
            of <ulink url="prop-ping-interval.html">wrapper.ping.interval</ulink>.
            The Wrapper will modify the value at run time if necessary to avoid
            problems.
        </para>
        <para>
            In normal operation, the Wrapper pings the JVM once every 5 seconds
            to make sure that its process has not frozen up.  The ping timeout
            is the amount of time to allow for a response from the JVM before
            the Wrapper assumes that it is hung and restarts it.
        </para>
        <para>
            This same property also controls the amount of time that the JVM will
            allow to pass without being pinged by the Wrapper.  If the Wrapper
            does not ping the JVM for longer than the specified timeout, it will
            exit allowing the Wrapper to resynch by launching a new JVM.   This
            also makes sure that the JVM will exit if the Wrapper process is
            terminated abnormally.  (By killing the Wrapper process in the Windows
            Task Manager, or using kill -9 on Unix systems.)
        </para>
        <para>
            With the addition of the
            <ulink url="prop-cpu-timeout.html">wrapper.cpu.timeout</ulink>
            property, there is now almost no reason why you should ever need
            to change this property.  The only reasons why you should be
            getting ping timeouts are if the system is under heavy load or
            if the JVM is really hung.  The CPU timeout should now detect
            any problems in with CPU.
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <simpara><emphasis>Example:</emphasis></simpara>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[wrapper.ping.timeout=30]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <warning>
            <simpara>
                While the ability is there.  Be aware that
                setting this property to 0 or some large value will mean
                that the Wrapper's ability to detect a JVM hang as it is
                running will be disabled.
            </simpara>
            <simpara>
                Also note that if the Wrapper process is killed abnormally or
                God forbid crashes, then the JVM will never attempt to resynch
                with the Wrapper.  If the Wrapper was running as an NT service
                at the time, it may be necessary to then reboot the machine to
                stop Java process.  With normal ping timeouts, the JVM would
                exit on its own after a few seconds.
            </simpara>
        </warning>
    </section>
</chapter>
