<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../dtd/docbook/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ********************************************************************
     $Id$
     ******************************************************************** -->

<chapter id="prop-ignore-signals">
    <title>wrapper.ignore_signals Property</title>
    <section>
        <title>Configuration Property Overview</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html">Configuration Property Overview</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="props-advanced.html">Advanced Properties</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html#name">Property List by Name</ulink>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>wrapper.ignore_signals</title>
        <para>
            Controls whether or not the Wrapper should ignore system signals.
            If this is set to True, the Wrapper will not respond to TERM or INT
            signals on UNIX or CTRL-C events on Windows.  Defaults to false.
        </para>
        <para>
            On UNIX systems, some backup programs that run as cron jobs will
            send out system wide TERM signals that can cause the Wrapper to
            shutdown.  These signals can be ignored by setting this property
            to true.
        </para>
        <para>
            In most cases, it is not necessary or desirable to manually configure
            this property.  The sh script that ships with the Wrapper can be
            configured to stop the wrapper by using an anchor file by simply
            uncommenting the <literal moreinfo="none">IGNORE_SIGNALS</literal>
            setting at the top section of the script.  This will cause the
            script to start and stop the Wrapper with the
            <ulink url="prop-anchorfile.html">wrapper.anchorfile</ulink>
            property enabled.  The anchor file makes it possible for the script
            to cause the Wrapper to shutdown by deleting it.  The normal method
            is to send the Wrapper a TERM signal.
        </para>
        <para>
            If the script is passed the 'console' command,
            to run in the current shell, it will still respond to system
            signals, including CTRL-C.   When the 'start' command is used,
            the Wrapper will be launched as a daemon process and will ignore
            all INT and TERM signals.  The Wrapper can then be stopped by
            executing the sh script with the 'stop' command or by manually
            deleting the anchor file.
        </para>
        <para>
            On Windows, SHUTDOWN and LOGOFF events are handled normally
            regardless of the value of this property.  The system would kill
            the application in any event should it fail to exit in a timely
            manner.  Note that LOGOFF events are always ignored if the
            Wrapper is running as an NT service.
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <simpara><emphasis>Example:</emphasis></simpara>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[wrapper.ignore_signals=true]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <para>
            If the ignore_signals property is not used in conjunction with
            the <ulink url="prop-anchorfile.html">wrapper.anchorfile</ulink>
            property, then the Wrapper will ignore system signals and not
            have any way to shut it down.  In such cases is it the responsibility
            of the Java application to provide a mechanism for shutting down
            the application.  This is done by either calling
            <literal moreinfo="none">WrapperManager.stop()</literal>
            or <literal moreinfo="none">System.exit()</literal>.
        </para>
        <note>
            <para>
                If you are planning on setting this property manually, It is
                suggested that you wait until your application's ability to
                reliably shutdown on its own has been fully tested.
            </para>
        </note>
        <warning>
            <simpara>
                If this property is set to true then you will not be able to
                tell the Wrapper to quit externally.  On Windows, CTRL-C will
                no longer function, and on UNIX systems CTRL-C or regular kill
                signals will also be ignored.  This means that on UNIX, the
                scripts provided with the Wrapper will not be able to stop the
                JVM unless the <literal moreinfo="none">IGNORE_SIGNALS</literal>
                setting in the script was uncommented before starting the
                Wrapper.
            </simpara>
            <simpara>
                On UNIX, the process can still be forcibly stopped using a
                <literal moreinfo="none">kill -9</literal>, but doing so will
                kill the Wrapper but leave the JVM running.  The JVM will exit
                on its own after its ping timeout has expired but all console
                output after the Wrapper was killed will be lost.
            </simpara>
            <simpara>
                On Windows, the Wrapper and its JVM can be forcibly killed from
                the Task Manager if the Wrapper was run as a console application.
                If run as a service, the Wrapper can still be stopped normally.
            </simpara>
        </warning>
    </section>
</chapter>
