<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../dtd/docbook/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ********************************************************************
     $Id$
     ******************************************************************** -->

<chapter id="prop-shutdown-timeout">
    <title>wrapper.shutdown.timeout Property</title>
    <section>
        <title>Configuration Property Overview</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html">Configuration Property Overview</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="props-advanced.html">Advanced Properties</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html#name">Property List by Name</ulink>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>wrapper.shutdown.timeout</title>
        <para>
            Number of seconds to allow between the time that the Wrapper asks
            the JVM to shutdown and the time that the JVM side of the Wrapper
            responds that it is stopping.  0 means never time out.  Defaults to
            30 seconds.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you are experiencing timeout problems as your application is
            shutting down, you may want to consider extending this timeout.
            This can happen in cases where the shutdown code within the
            application takes a long time to complete.  As a test, try setting
            this property to something like 300 (5 minutes) and see if this
            makes the problem go away.
        </para>
        <para>
            If the application still times out quicker than the 5 minute test
            timeout, then the problem may be in a later phase of shutdown.
            Take a look at the
            <ulink url="prop-jvm-exit-timeout.html">wrapper.jvm_exit.timeout</ulink>
            property.
        </para>
        <para>
            If the application still times out after waiting the full 5 minutes
            then you will have to do some debugging of your application to see
            what is taking so long.  If it is possible to speed up the
            application's shutdown phase, that would be best.  Otherwise set
            the timeout to a value that allows the application to shutdown
            cleanly.
        </para>
        <para>
            It is best to choose a value which is long enough to let the
            application run reliably, but short enough that the Wrapper will
            react as quickly as possible in the event of an actual JVM hang.
        </para>
        <para>
            If the shutdown procedure sometimes takes a long time.  One
            alternative to setting a long timeout is to periodically call the 
            <literal moreinfo="none">WrapperManager.signalStopping(n)</literal>
            method.  This method gives the application the ability to request
            more time to shutdown, while at the same time assuring the Wrapper
            that the JVM is alive and well.
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <simpara><emphasis>Example:</emphasis></simpara>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[wrapper.shutdown.timeout=30]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <warning>
            <simpara>
                While the ability is there.  Be aware that
                setting this property to 0 or some large value will mean
                that the Wrapper's ability to detect a JVM hang during the
                shutdown phase will be disabled.
            </simpara>
        </warning>
    </section>
</chapter>
