<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../dtd/docbook/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ********************************************************************
     $Id$
     ******************************************************************** -->

<chapter id="props-cascading">
    <title>Cascading Configuration Files</title>
    <section>
        <title>Configuration Property Overview</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="properties.html">Configuration Property Overview</ulink>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Cascading Configuration Files</title>
        <para>
            Starting with version 3.0.0, it is possible to specify include
            files within a configuration file.  This is useful where there is a need
            to override default values without modifying the main
            configuration file.
        </para>
        <para>
            Include files are specified by placing a line in the configuration file
            with the following syntax:
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <screen format="linespecific"><![CDATA[#include ../conf/wrapper2.conf]]></screen>
        </informalexample>
        <para>
            If the specified file can not be located for any reason then it
            is ignored.  This makes it easy to specify a series of optional
            include files which users may or may not create.
        </para>
        <para>
            The location of the include definition in a file is important.
            Any properties defined before the include can be overridden where
            as properties set after the include file will override any
            settings in the include files.  This rule applies to the contents
            of include files as well.
        </para>
        <para>
            If relative paths to the include files are specified, be aware
            that all paths must be relative to the location of the Wrapper
            working directory.  By default, this is the location of the Wrapper.exe
            on Windows, or the script used to launch the Wrapper on UNIX.  The
            working directory can be changed using the
            <ulink url="prop-working-dir.html">wrapper.working.dir</ulink> property.
        </para>
        <para>
            Include files can be nested up to 10 levels deep.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
